A Guide to the IAWA Small Collections, 1907-2013
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
- Persons and Associations
  - Smithson, Alison, drawings, 1982, Extent: 1.75 cubic feet (Oversize 5)
    1928-1993. Architect of London, England. Educated at the University of Durham, and worked at the London County Council until she formed a partnership in 1950 with her husband Peter Smithson. Collection consists of three drawings Smithson submitted for the Parc de la Villette (Paris) competition in 1982.
  - Smolina, Nadejda Ivanovna, papers, 1990-1997, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 18)
    Smolina is the Head of the State Museum of Architecture (MUAR) Academic Library in Moscow. The collection contains photocopies of two diplomas and one medal awarded to Smolina's publication Traditions of Symmetry in Architecture. Moscow: Stroyizdat, 1990, and three architecture conference programs from the West-East series (Architecture of the World 3. West-East: Tradition of Antiquity in Architecture, VNIITAG-MARHI, Moscow: Architectura, 1994. and Architecture of the World 6. West-East: 2000 Years of the Architecture Book, VNIITAG-MARHI, Moscow: Architectura, 1997.)
    Separated Materials
    Four volumes (in Russian) have been cataloged and placed in the Rare Book Collection:
    Smolina, Nadejda Ivanovna. Traditions of Symmetry in Architecture. Moscow: Stroyizdat, 1990.
    Architecture of the World 3. West-East: Tradition of Antiquity in Architecture, VNIITAG-MARHI, Moscow: Architectura, 1994.
    Architecture of the World 6. West-East: 2000 Years of the Architecture Book, VNIITAG-MARHI, Moscow: Architectura, 1997.
    Ametova, Maria. Salomea Gelfer: to the Jubilee of an Architect, MOscow: MUAR, 2006.
  - Spear, Laurinda, biographical information, 2005 and undated, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 7)
    In 1977, Spear forms the modernist architecture firm Arquitectonica in Miami, Fl with Bernardo Fort-Brescia. The firm has expanded to New York, Los Angeles, Paris, Hong Kong, Shanghai, Manila, Lima, Buenos Aires, and San Paulo. A fellow of The American Institute of Archiects, she is the winner of the AIA Silver Medal and the Rome Prize in Architecture and is a member of the Interior Design Hall of Fame.
  - Speigel, Susan, postcards, 1985, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 7)
    The collection consists of a book of limited edition postcards of architectural sketches that Canadian architect Susan Speigel drew entitled Composition as Explanation: The Plan. Drawings by Speigel can be viewed on the VT ImageBase. Inventory available.
  - Stamatova, Nadya, papers, 1900-1999, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 7)
    Graduated in 1981 from the University of Architecture and Construction in Sofia, Bulgaria. In 1990 she opened a private firm "ADA-2-Nadya Stamatova", in Varna, Bulgaria (Architectural And Artistic Design Studio ADA-2). The collection consists of her résumé and photocopies of portions of her work. Inventory available.
  - Stan, Sally Bould, biographical material, 1972, 2006, 2008, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 7)
    Born 1917. An architect from Lafayette, California, Stan graduated from the University of California at Berkeley in 1939. She designed her first home in 1948 and retired in 1998. She worked largely for contractors, focusing on residential housing, subdivisions, and single-family dwellings. Materials include a memorial program, a short biography, and two biographical letters. See also the SALLY BOULD STAN ARCHITECTURAL PAPERS, 1940-1997 and VT Imagebase for additional materials and digital images.
  - Steinegger, Elisabeth, biographical material, 1969-1984, Extent: 0.2 cubic feet (Box 7)
    Born 1933. Partner of Steinegger & Hartmann, Architekten, in Binningen, Switzerland. A curriculum vitae and seven catalogs detailing the designs she made with her husband.
  - Steinmesch, H. May, papers, 1946, 1967-1968 and undated, Extent: 2.0 cubic feet (Oversize 16)
    1893-1979. Founding member and National President (1928-1930) of the Association of Women in Architecture. Materials consist of a photograph of (Henrietta) May Steinmesch; an article, "A Short History of the Association of Women in Architecture," with a brief biography; two site plans, and four slides of her architectural designs. Also has materials on VT Imagebase.
  - Stevens, Mary Otis, articles, 1956-1991, Extent: 0.1 cu.ft. (Box 14)
    Mary Otis Stevens graduated from MIT with a bachelors' degree in 1956. A protégé of Walter Gropius she is considered one of the most important female architects in the Northeast during the 1960s and 1970s. She partnered with her husband Thomas McNulty from 1956 to 1969, creating in 1965, one of their most influential projects the Lincoln House.
    In 1975, Stevens founded the Design Guild, a collaborative architectural practice focused on non-profit clients, historic preservation and adaptive re-use; the Guild disbanded in 1991. The collection includes photocopied material (including articles and photographs of models) of various projects: Stevens' MIT thesis; a proposed Catholic Church; house on Kittery Point; Lincoln House; and the Design Guild.
    For more information on Mary Otis Stevens please see the Mary Otis Stevens Collection at the MIT Museum or the Susana Torre Architectural Papers Ms1990-016
  - Stocker-Mergenthaler, Beth, papers, Extent: 1.6 cubic feet (Box 7, Box 14)
    Architect and performance artist in Basel, Switzerland. Collection contains postcards, pamphlets, a poster, and a magazine, Merian: Basel, in which she and her husband are cited.
  - Stoilova, Ljubinka K., biographical material, 2006 and undated., Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 7)
    Ljubinka Stoilova is an architect and architectural researcher who has published articles and monographs about theory and history of 19th and 20th century architecture. She has also helped organize over 10 documentary exhibitions in Bulgaria, Austria, and The Czech Republic. Her collection includes an exhibition postcard and a curriculum vitae that includes a small color image. The 2006 exhibition catalog that she wrote with Irina Genova, Presences/Absences: Women Artists and Architects in the Modern Art of Bulgaria is in ADDISON and available in the Special Collections Rare Book Room.
  - Sutton, Sharon E., artwork, 1975-1979, 1999, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 7)
    The collection is a set of three 5.5" x 10.5" Sutton prints, a one-page biography, and Sutton's résumé from 1999. Inventory available. Also has materials on VT Imagebase.
  - Svigelj-Cernigoj, Monjca, pamphlet and résumé, 1998, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 7)
    Architect of Ljubljana, Slovenia.
  - Syrkus, Helena, biographical material, 1983, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 7)
    1900-1982. Architect of Warsaw, Poland. Biographical sketch of Syrkus written by Syrkus's sister, Irena Wilcryinski. Materials also include a typed transcript of Wilcryinski's manuscript biography.
  - Taranto, Lisa, CD, 2006, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 7)
    The collection consists of a CD showing ceramic artwork from a show by Virgina Tech architecture school alumna Lisa Taranto in 2006. It includes color images, movie files, architectural drawings for ceramic buildings, and text files with biographical information.
  - Thompson, Jane, biographical material, 1976, 1979, 1990, 1998, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 7)
    Architect of Cambridge, Massachusetts, partner of Benjamin Thompson & Associates, Inc. (1967-1994), principal of Thompson Design Group (1994-2010). Contributed to the design of public spaces including Ghiradelli Square (San Francisco), Faneuil Hall (Boston), and South Street Seaport (New York City) while with Benjamin Thompson & Associates. Master plan projects with Thompson Design Group include Navy Pier (Chicago), Governor’s Island (New York City), North Coast Harbor (Cleveland), Buffalo Bayou (Houston). Collection consists of biographical material and reprints of articles about her work.
  - Tolzer, Maria, papers, 1956, 1985, Extent: 0.3 cubic feet (Box 18)
    Architect of Vienna, Austria. A book on architecture, Beruflicher Weidegang Und Lebenslauf, a photograph she contributed to Neues Wohnen (1956), and three 1985 catalogs--Gestalten Staff Nur Moblieren, Die Kleinen Aufgaben, and Architekture mit Sozialem Vorzeichen.
  - Toma, Nicoleta, papers, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 7)
    Architect in Bucharest. Papers consist of a résumé and photocopies of several project drawings and photographs.
  - Topelson de Grinberg, Sara, brochure, 1996, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 7)
    Brochure about Topelson de Grinberg and some of her projects, 1996.
  - Tranberg, Lene, papers, undated, Extent: 0.1 cu.ft. (Box 20)
    (1956- ). Danish architect who is the head architect and co-founder of Lundgaard & Tranberg. Collection includes several overlays for an undocumented space and 2 photographs of a residence at St. Kannikestraede 6, Copenhagen.
  - Treant-Mathe, Juliette, booklet, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 7)
    The collection consists of a booklet, Gais Logis which has smaller pamphlets containing information about five French apartment complexes that Treant-Mathe designed. Inventory available.
  - Troeva, Vesselina Rousseva, biographical materials, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 7)
    Architect in Bulgaria. Materials include two curriculum vitaes and one card.
  - Tsevelma, Danzansharavyn, portfolio, 1992-1998, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 11)
    Collection includes a portfolio of one of Tsevelana's projects, the National Wrestling Palace in Ulaan-Baatar, Mongolia, with photocopies of drawings, photographs of the model of the project, and photographs of the Palace under construction. The project received the Laureate Prize from the Mongolian Union of Architects. Inventory available.
  - Tyutcheva, Narine, brochure, undated, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 7)
    Firm brochure.
  - Uncu, Ana, thesis, 1999, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 7)
    Architect in Bucharest, Romania. Thesis is titled "Historical research in archives and on the site for completing the General Urban Plan of the village of Valea Calugareasca, Prahova county and in view to develop a strategy to preserve the cultural and landscape treasures of this historic place, the hills of Dealu Mare". Inventory available.
  - Urbanke, Rosemarie, papers, 1978-1985, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 7)
    2 books from the 2011 accession were cataloged and placed in the Rare Book collection. Architectural Guidebook Neukolln Berlin by Chrintine Borgelt and Regina Jost, 2003 and Building for 100 years: Neukolln, a local architectural history published by the District Office Neukolln of Berlin, Department of Civil Engineering, 2005
    Born 1951. Architect of Berlin, Germany. Collection consists of a résumé, architectural drawings (1978-1985), photographs of her, and sketches of her daughter and abstract images. An addition was added to the collection in 2011 containing postcards taken by Urbanke featuring mosaic ceiling tiles in Neukolln Hall; a photo exhibit catalog titled "Between Watts and the Ganges," 2009; and color photocopies of buildings designed by Urbanke.
  - Vecsei, Eva Hollo, biographical material and brochure, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 7)
    Architect of Montreal, Canada. Member of the Order of Architects of Quebec, Fellow of the Royal Architectural Institute of Canada, and an Honorary Fellow of the American Institute of Architects. Received a diploma in Architecture at the Budapesti Muszaki Egyetem (University of Technical Sciences, Budapest) (1952). Collection consists of biographical material including curriculum vitae and a autobiographical chronicle of her life titled Eva's Chronicle, 1930-2009, as well as, a flyer advertising her firm, Vecsei Architectes of Montreal, which she was co-principal of with her husband Andrew Vecsei. See also the Canadian Encyclopedia entry on Vecsei.
  - Veltcheva, Maria, article, 2006, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 7)
    Photocopy of article "Paris, Berlin, Rome L'intériorisation de l'extérieur" written by Veltcheva from Urbanisme no.346, 2 pages, 2006.
  - Vilches, Cecilia, e-mail, 2005, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 7)
    E-mail print outs containing information about Vilches's Theme Furniture, 9 pages, 2005
  - Vinciarelli, Lauretta, artwork, 1993 and undated, Extent: 3.0 cubic feet (Box 14)
    Collection consists of eleven untitled tempera drawings on boards by American Architect Lauretta Vinciarelli, exhibition timeline, and curriculum vitae.
  - Virginia Women in Architecture: An Exhibit Highlighting the Work of Women Architects in Virginia exhibit literature, 1988, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 7)
    Literature for the "Virginia Women in Architecture: An Exhibit Highlighting the Work of Women Architects in Virginia" exhibit. The exhibit planned by the Virginia Women in Architecture Committee and the Virginia Society, AIA was intended to complement the National AIA Exhibit "That Exceptional One: Women in Architecture, 1888-1988."
  - Vitzthum, Sandra, curriculum vitae, 2000, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 7)
    Collection is composed of her curriculum vitae.
  - Vytlacil, Anne, curriculum vitae, 1994, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 7)
    Born 1936. Practiced in Washington, D.C.
  - Wagner, Anne Gabriele, curriculum vitae, 1990, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 7)
    Born in 1963. Architect of Vienna, Austria. Collection is composed of her curriculum vitae.
  - Wainstein-Krasuk, Olga, papers, 1987-1991 and undated, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 7)
    Born 1939. Architect of Buenos Aires, Argentina. Director of the Center of Studies of Habitat and Housing sponsored by the Organization of American States and the School of Architecture, Design and Urbanism of the University of Buenos Aires. The Center studies ways to effectively and economically design and build housing and makes recommendations to the OAS on its findings. Collection consists of a brief explanation of the Center's work and projects and a survey designed by the Center to evaluate a building's accessibility to the handicapped. Also includes an extensive brochure of works by her firm, Bielus, Goldemberg, Waistein-Krasuk, Architects, from 1966 to 1981.
  - Weisberg, Sarelle T., Papers, 1982-1999, 2006, Extent: 0.3 cubic feet (Box 8)
    FAIA; New York Architect and principal of Anhouse + Weisberg Associates. Educated at Vassar College (B.A., Art History, 1950), and Columbia University (M. Arch., 1972). Supervising architect/engineer and airport planner for the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey (1979-1984). Downstate Design Manager for the New York State Facilities Development Corporation (1984-1994), where she managed construction projects for the New York State Office of Mental Health and Office of Mental Retardation/Development Disabilities. Collection consists of the dossier Weisberg prepared when applying for Fellowship in the AIA and other biographical and professional information.
  - Weiss-Koenig, Annaliese, portfolio, 1988 and undated, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 8)
    Born 1930. Architect of Inzlingen, Germany. Collection consists of fourteen photographs and eight sets of architectural drawings for residences and a hotel. Also includes an autobiographical essay.
  - Whitman, Bertha Yerex, papers, 1932, 1971-1978, and undated, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 8)
    Born 1892. First female to receive a bachelors of science from the University of Michigan in architecture in 1920. Practiced in Chicago, Illinois. Materials include correspondence and photographs.
  - Wilburn, Leila Ross, biographical information, 2005, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 8)
    Born 1885, died 1967. Architect of Georgia. Wilburn studied at Agnes Scott College and apprenticed with an architectural firm before opening her own firm in 1909. She is best known for her published "pattern books" of arts and crafts style houses. The collection consists of a copy of the nomination form to name Wilburn a 2003 Georgia Woman of Achievement and photocopies of supporting research material compiled by James McManus. The Leila Ross Wilburn Collection is housed in the Kenan Research Center of the Atlanta History Center.
  - Winchester, Sarah Pardee, article, 1975, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 8)
    Born 1839. Died 1922. Article entitled "Sarah Winchester" by Esther Talbot published in The Rosicrucian Digest July 1975.
  - Winter-Bracher, Ingeborg, papers, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 8)
    Born 1923. Architect of Munich, Germany. Papers includes a brief typescript autobiographical essay, photographs, and a book, Bauten Und Ziele, written by her husband to which she contributed. The book is cataloged separately in the Addison library catalog, and is available through the Special Collections Reading Room.
  - Women in Architecture (AIA) papers, 2001-2004, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 8)
    Printouts of meeting agendas.
  - Women's Design Service publications, 1988 and undated, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 8)
    Technical aid agency providing a resource center, library, and consultation services on issues related to women and the design of the built environment in the greater London area, Great Britain. Materials consist of literature published by the Women's Design Service about various problems for those disadvantaged by the design of the public environment and about improving play areas for children. Also includes issues of Women and the Built Environment.
  - Women's Development Corporation (WCD) informational literature, 1990 and undated, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 8)
    Corporation formed in 1980 in Providence, Rhode Island, to design and develop rental housing for low-income women and children. Collection includes articles about apartments WDC has designed and a brochure packet about the corporation.
  - Women's International Network (WIN) papers, 1994-1995, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 8)
    The collection includes a publication that covers news events throughout the world that are relevant to women, a 1994 publication, a letter from the editor, Fran P. Hosken, and meeting announcements.
  - Women's School of Planning and Architecture inventory of records, 1972-1992, and undated, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 8)
    An experimental summer school in environmental design, this is a copy of the "Inventory of Records" in the Sophia Smith Collection at Smith College.
  - Wood, Joan, papers, 1990-1994, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 8)
    After earning her Bachelor of Architecture degree from M.I.T. in 1960, she established Joan Wood Architects. Most of her firm's work can be found in New England. The collection consists of a catalog of Joan Wood Architects work, her résumé, and articles from The Boston Globe about her firm. Inventory available.
  - Xiaowei, Luo papers, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 8)
    Born 1925. President of the Architectural Society of Shanghai, China and visiting lecturer and professor at numerous institutions around the world. Includes a curriculum vitae and correspondence.
  - Zaglaniki, Loukia, papers 1988, Extent: 1.5 cubic feet (Oversize 8)
    Architect of Athens, Greece. Materials consist of four panels and an article in an architectural text on "A preliminary study regarding the constructions of the protective roofing and the tumulus restoration of the Vergina royal tombs." The text was removed and placed in the Rare Book Collection.
  - Zahle, Mette, published works, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 20)
    Architect of the Netherlands. Collection contains a reprint from the Danish architectural journal ARKITEKTEN written by Zahle titled "A Dutch House designed by Jan Verhoeven." An English summary is present.
- Publications
  - Architect: the Magazine of the American Institute of Architects, June 2014 (Box P1)
    Magazine features Julia Morgan (1872-1957), an American architect from California who was posthumously awarded the AIA Gold Medal in 2014. Morgan was the first woman to receive the honor.
    Morgan, Julia
  - Aula: Architecture and Urbanism in Las Américas, Spring 1999 (Box P1)
    "Claiming the Public Space: The Mothers of Plazo de Mayo," photocopy of article written by Susana Torre.
  - Casas Contemporaneas del Ecuador, 2002 (Box P1)
  - Design Catalog: 2012 catalog of Nanimarquina rug collection, 2012 (Box P1)
  - Exhibit Catalog: Arquitectas de Puerto Rico, el Caribe, y la Florida: su obra: [exhibición] 14 Noviembre al 31 Diciembre 1991 Galeria de Exposiciones del Chase Manhattan Bank, Hato Rey, Puerto Rico, 1991 (Box P1)
  - Exhibit Catalog: The Feminine Presence in Israeli Architecture, catalog of an exhibition, 2009 (Box P1)
    Exhibit catalog (2009) edited by Sigal Davidi that chronicles the first exhibition of female architects in the history of Israeli architecture. The exhibit opened at the Union of Architects in Jaffa (2007) and featured the built projects of 22 "veteran and new architects." The projects were also accompanied by a short manifesto that the architects were asked to write. A video, "A skirt of concrete and cement," directed by architect Vered Fluk was shown as part of the exhibit and the DVD of this film is included with the catalog.
  - Florida Architect, Women in Architecture issue, July/August 1992 (Box P1)
  - Habitar: Revista del Colegio de Arquitectos de Pinchincha [Colegio de Arquitectos del Ecuador] nos. 43-44. (Box P1)
  - Journal of Architectural Education, Gender and Multiculturalism in Architecture edition, v. 47 no.1 - September 1993 (Box P1)
    General
    see Art and Architecture Library for complete holdings
  - Mujer y arquitectura, dossier revista 8 de Marzo no. 34, 1999 (Box P1)
  - Perspectiva [Colegio de Arqitectos del Ecuador] no. 60, April 2003 (Box P1)
  - Perspective: Society of Architectural Historians/Texas Chapter v. XI no.2, December 1980 (Box P1)
  - Perspectives: the Journal of the Ontario Association of Architects vol.2, no.2 Spring 1994 (Box P1)
  - Women: East--West, January 1989 (Box P1)
    A newsletter by an for researcher's interested in women's studies and questions of gender and family life in Central and East Europe and the territories of the Soviet Union.
- Subject Files
  - Argentinian Women Architects (Box S1)
    Spreadsheet print out listing the first 11 eleven women to register with the Consejo Profesional de Arquitectura y Urbanismo (CPAU) in Argentina. Also present are short CPAU biographies for 8 of these 11 women.
  - Bauhaus, Female Pioneers 2013 (Box S1)
    New York Times article by Alice Rawsthorn (March 22, 2013) titled 'Female Pioneers of the Bauhaus' featuring Gertrud Arndt, Benita Koch-Otte, and Lou Scheper-Berkenkamp.
  - Bulgarian Women Architects (Box S1)
    article by Milka Bliznakov [?]
  - Children -- Designs for Children in the IAWA (Box S1)
    article by Milka Bliznakov
  - Cuban Women, 1968 (Box S1)
    An article published in the Miami Herald about Cuban professional women in the Miami area. Article focuses on Matilde Ponce a prize-winning architect in Cuba and her opportunites in the United States.
  - Interior Decoration 2002-2003
    Emma Ferry's article 'Decorators May be Compared to Doctors' An Analysis of Rhoda and Agnes Garrett's Suggestions for House Decoration in Painting, Woodwork, and Furniture (1876) pblished in Journal of Design History vol.16 no.1 (2003)
    Related Materials
    'Suggestions for house decoration in painting, woodwork, and furniture' (1876). By Rhoda and Agnes Garrett is available through the Special Collections Reading Room SPEC SMALL TX309 .G35 1876
  - Textile works, 2010 (Box S1)
    2 photocopy sheets featuring the works of Kvadrat Cloud DK, Denmark and Anni Albers, Black Mountain College.
  - Vienna Architecture, 2002 (Box S1)
    Traveling exhibit produced by the Austrian Cultural Forum NYC titled 'inner scene vienna.' Material includes informational literature and a CD-ROM catalog.
  - Women in Architecture Symposium held at Virginia Tech, January 1972 (Box S1)